# **ALEX PTAKHIN**

- Email me@aptakhin.name (preferred) / Mobile +49 151 207 230 26
- Linkedin linkedin.com/in/aptakhin / Github github.com/aptakhin

### SUMMARY

Strong full-stack and backend developer experience focusing on minding out of job positions for customer happiness. Have experience with designing and supporting highly loaded services and tech-leading up to 4 developers. Consulting for teams better processes and engineering grow.

### **EXPERIENCE**

September 2022 – now N months

### Senior Python Fullstack Developer, Berlin

Prestatech - b2b smartlending solutions company.

Hiring. Work on whole system observability.

Jul 2020 – May 2022 22 months

### **Data Engineer Tech Lead, Moscow**

Admitad is an international company to drive sales and earn online. Headquater office locates in Germany, Heilbronn. Currently, Admitad has offices in seven countries around the globe and over 900 employees.

- Achieved 99.95% reliability SLA goals and further developing for internal Data Warehouse product
- Negotiation and contracting with ClickHouse tech consulting and cloud provider
- Integration testing: minus half an hour of developers handwork per task (-70% time)
- Made HTTP streaming of millions of products from databases with huge gigabyte files
- Managed team of 4 middle developers, their development and hiring

Apr 2018 – Jul 2020 2 years

#### Python Developer/Tech lead

Nanosemantics.ai is Russia's leading artificial intelligence technology developer. Founded in 2005, it specializes in applied linguistics, internet technologies and quality client service solutions.

- Lead engineer role audience parser startup for Vk.com social network. Managing: 1 developer. Made architecture for horizontal scaled crawling process with Vk.com authorization ~6000 rps from one VDS
- Lead engineer of chatbot IDE backend: architecture and development. Added delivery process Gitlab CI/CD on top of Kubernetes
- Tech lead of markup data service for machine learning. Prototype developing support and new growing design architecture for b2b service
- Developer: various integrations and short-term projects e.g. Turing contest asyncio backend Turing contest with 100 rps on small VPS

Dec 2014 – Dec 2017 3 years

#### **Software Developer Engineer**

Yandex is a technology company that builds intelligent products and services powered by machine learning. Yandex, which has 30 offices worldwide, has been listed on the NASDAQ since 2011.

- Developed the regression testing and releasing pipeline for the AB-testing metrics platform. Mades possible regular weekly releases with higher quality (less 3-5 longdebugging bugs in a month)
- Made the storage of the experiment's metrics data and the instrument for analyzing them. The tool reduces experiments time and money costs
- Anomalies detection in time-series service: increased throughput and storage x10 from unsupported cloud stack

Apr 2013 - Dec 2014 ~1.5 year

#### **Software Developer Engineer**

NIIAS – one of the research institutes of Russian Railway (RZD).

 Developed diagnostic software for displaying system component's state in wireless railway solution. Dumps history and plays it for debugging system problems

### **TECHNICAL STRENGTHS**

Primary stack Python3, asyncio, aiohttp, aio-libs, pytest/unittest

Secondary stack JavaScript, C++

Deploying Gitlab CI/CD, Github Actions, Ansible, Azure cloud, Docker, Kubernetes

Management Hiring, growing, Agile processes tuning on sociotechnical system

Databases/brokers PostgreSQL, ClickHouse, Kafka, RabbitMQ, Redis

## **LANGUAGES**

English B2

German A1

Russian native

# COMMUNITIES, CERTIFICATES AND OTHER STUFF

- from Dec 2022. My substack <u>wholesystems.substack.com</u>
- Nov 2022. Cloud Academy: Architecting Microsoft Azure Solutions, completed [cert]
- from May 2020. Podlodka Teamlead Crew, community member [www]
- Dec 2020. Negotiations simulator Skillslab, completed [cert]
- Dec 2020. Change Basics Changers school, completed [cert]
- Nov 2020. Become teamlead by Fedor Borshev & Mariana Onysko, co-organizer [cert]
- Sep 2020. Product Mindset Intermediate, completed [cert]

## **EDUCATION**

Sep 2009 – Jun 2014,

Master's degree of Mechanics-Mathematics Faculty at Moscow State University,

~5 years Theoretical Mechanics and Robotics